[{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following gases has a characteristic pungent smell, turns red litmus paper blue and forms dense white fumes with hydrogen chloride gas?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["N<sub>3<\/sub>","N<sub>2<\/sub>O","Cl<sub>2<\/sub>","NH<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Commercial bleaching can be carried out using<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Sulphur (IV) oxide and ammonia","Hydrogen sulphide and chlorine","Chlorine and sulphur(iv) oxide","ammonia and chlorine"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Mineral acids are usually added to commercial hydrogen peroxide to&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["oxidize it","decompose it","minimize its decomposition","reduce it to water  and oxygen"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following compounds will burn with a brick-red colour in a non-luminous Bunsen flame?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["LiCl","NaCl","CaCl<sub>2<\/sub>","MgCl<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The purest form of iron which contains only about 0.1% carbon is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["pig iron","wrought iron","cast iron","iron pryrite"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>A common characteristic between zinc and the other transition elements is the ability to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["have variable oxidation states","form complex ions","act as a catalyst","form a coloured ions"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following metals is the least reactive?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Pb","Sn","Hg","Au"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Geometric isomerism can exist in&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Hex-3-ene","Hexane","Prop-1-ene","3-methyl but-1-ene"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Isomers of C<\/strong><b>\u2083<\/b><strong style=\"font-size: 0.875rem;\">H<\/strong><b>\u2088<\/b><strong style=\"font-size: 0.875rem;\">O are&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1-propanol and 2-propanol","1-propanol and 1-propanol","2-propanol and 2-propanone","2-propanol and 1-propanal"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Carbonhydrates are large molecules with the molecular formula C<sub>x<\/sub>(H2O)<sub>y<\/sub> in which of the following pairs is x equal to y?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["glucose and starch","maltose and fructose","sucrose and fructose","maltose and starch"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>A compound contains 40.0% C. 6-7% H and 53.3% O. If the molecular mass of the compounds is 180, its molecular formula is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["CH<sub>2<\/sub>O","C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>O","C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub>","C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>12<\/sub>O<sub>6<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The alkyne that will give a white precipitation with silver trioxonitrate (V) is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["CH<sub>3<\/sub> CH<sub>2<\/sub>  C = C CH<sub>2<\/sub> CH<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub> C = C CH<sub>2<\/sub> CH<sub>2<\/sub> CH<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub> CH<sub>2<\/sub> CH<sub>2<\/sub> CH<sub>2<\/sub> C = CH","CH<sub>3<\/sub> CH<sub>2<\/sub> CH<sub>2<\/sub> C = C CH<sub>2<\/sub> CH<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The oxidation number of boron is NaBH<sub>4<\/sub><\/strong><\/p>","options":["-3","-1","+1","+3"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Presence of NaCl in ice will<\/strong><\/p>","options":["lower the boiling point of NaCl","increase the melting point of NaCl","make NaCl impure","lower the freezing point of ice"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>What are the values of x, y and z in the equation below?<\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p><strong>xNH<sub>3<\/sub> + yO<sub>2<\/sub> -&gt; zNO + 6H<sub>2<\/sub>O<\/strong><\/p>","options":["2,3,4","4,5,4","6,5,4","2,3,4"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Calculate the volume of CO<sub>2<\/sub> measured at s.t.p produced on heating 250g of potassium hydrogen trioxocarbonate (iv) strongly. (K=39, H=1, C=12, O=16)<\/strong><\/p>","options":["28dm<sup>3<\/sup>","2.8dm<sup>3<\/sup>","5.6dm<sup>3<\/sup>","11.2dm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>The boiling points of water, ethanol, methyl benzene and butan-2-ol are 373.0k, 351.3k, 383.6k and 372.5k respectively. Which liquid has the highest vapour pressure at 323.0k?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["water","methyl benzene","ethanol","butan-2-ol"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>The conclusion from Rutherford's alpha-scattering experiment is that<\/strong><\/p>","options":["atoms are mostly empty space with a small nucleus","emissions from radioactive substance consists of three main components","there is a nuclear pull on orbital electrons","electrons are deflected by both magnetic and electric fields"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Elements P, Q and R have atomic numbers 9, 16 and 20 respectively. Which of them would gain electron(s) during ionic bonding?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Q and R","P and R","P and Q","P, Q and R"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is an acid salt?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["(NH<sub>4<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub> CO<sub>3<\/sub>","CH COONa","KHSO<sub>4<\/sub>","MgSO<sub>4<\/sub> 7H<sub>2<\/sub>O"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Cr<sub>2<\/sub>O<sup>-2<\/sup><sub>7<\/sub> + 14H + 6I -&gt; 2Cr<sup>3<\/sup> + 3I<sub>2<\/sub> + 7H<sub>2<\/sub>O. The changes in the oxidation number of oxygen in the equation above is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0","1","2","7"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>During the electrolysis of CuSO<sub>4<\/sub> solution using PI electrode, which of the following occurs?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["acidity increase at the cathode","oxygen is liberated at the cathode","PH decrcaft   at the cathode","PH of solution increases"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>The solubility of a salt of molar mass 100g at 20<sup>o<\/sup>C is 0.34moldm<sup>-3<\/sup>. If 3.4g of salt dissolved completely in 250cm<sup>3<\/sup> of water at that temperature, the resulting solution is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["a suspension","saturated","unsaturated","supersaturated"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following ions is a pollution in drinking water even in trace quantities?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Ca<sup>2+<\/sup>","Pb<sup>2+<\/sup>","Mg<sup>2+<\/sup>","Fe<sup>2+<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Catalyst is important in chemical industry in that<\/strong><\/p>","options":["it affects the purity of the products","it affects the quantity of the products","it increases the time for reaching equilibrium","all of the above"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these alkanoic acids has a molecular mass of 88&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["propanoic acid","butanoic acid","pentanoic acid","but-2-ene"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Ethyne undergoes the following reactions except<\/strong><\/p>","options":["polymerization","addition","substitution","etherification"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>The partial pressure of N<sub>2<\/sub> in a container at 50<sup>o<\/sup>C in which there are 0.50mole of N<sub>2<\/sub> and 1.2mole of CO<sub>2<\/sub> at a pressure of 2.00 atmosphere is?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.6atm","0.5atm","0.40atm","1.6atm"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The major reason why chemical reaction occurs among elements is that they have the tendency to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["attain the nearest noble gas structure","become a metal","become a non metal","become a noble element"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Given that the pH of a solution of KOH is 12, what is the concentration of the OH ions?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.01mol\/dm<sup>3<\/sup>","1x10<sup>-12<\/sup>mol\/dm<sup>3<\/sup>","1x10<sup>14<\/sup>mol\/dm<sup>3<\/sup>","1x10<sup>-7<\/sup>mol\/dm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Two immiscible liquids with different boiling points can be separated by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["the use of separating funnel","evaporation","distillation","decantation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>A mixture of CaCl<sub>2<\/sub> and CaCO<sub>3<\/sub> in water can be separated by&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["evaporation","filtration","distillation","decantation"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Consider the reaction represented by<\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p><strong>xPb(NO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub> -&gt; 2PbO + yNO<sub>2<\/sub> + zO<sub>2<\/sub><\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p><strong>What are the values of x,y and z respectively?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["2,6,3","1,4,2","2,4,1","2,4,2"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>20cm<sup>3<\/sup> of H<sub>2<\/sub> mixed and separated with 100cm<sup>3<\/sup> of air containing 21% O<sub>2<\/sub>. Calculate the volume of the residual gases at 110<sup>o<\/sup>C<\/strong><\/p>","options":["31cm<sup>3<\/sup>","8.11cm<sup>3<\/sup>","90cm<sup>3<\/sup>","110cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>What is responsible for metallic bonding?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["sharing of electrons between the metal atoms","attraction between the atom nuclei and the cloud of electrons","transfer of electrons from one atom to another","attraction between positive and negative ions"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>25cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 1.5M solution of NaCl are added to 50cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 3M NaCl. The molar concentration of the resulting solution is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["2.5M","3M","2.25M","4.5M"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>A solution of salt formed form HCl and NH<sub>3<\/sub> solution is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["acidic","basic","complex","neutral"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following elements will burn in excess oxygen to form a product that is neutral to litmus?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["carbon","hydrogen","sulphur","sodium"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Pollution of underground water by metal ions is very likely in a soil that has high<\/strong><\/p>","options":["acidity","alkalinity","chloride content","nitrate content"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>For most reversible reactions<\/strong><\/p>","options":["the reaction rate increases with time","the reaction rate decreases with time","the rate stabilizes with time","the rate produces a curve with time"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following compounds will leave a metal and residue when heated?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Cu(NO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub>","AgNO<sub>2<\/sub>","K<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>2<\/sub>","Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the polymers contains nitrogen?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["nylon","PVC","polythene","cellulose"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>A red precipitate of copper(I) dicarbide is formed when ammonium solution of copper(I)chloride is introduced into<\/strong><\/p>","options":["CH\u2082 = CH-CH\u2082-CH\u2083","CH\u2083-CH\u2082-C=CH","CH\u2083-CH\u2082-CH\u2082-CH\u2083","CH\u2083-C=C-CH"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>A mixture of iron and sulphur can be separated in<\/strong><\/p>","options":["steam","dilute hydrochloric  acid","dilute sodium hydroxide","benzene"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Calculate the minimum volume of oxygen that is required for complete combustion of a mixture of 20cm<sup>3<\/sup> of CO and 10cm<sup>3<\/sup> of hydrogen<\/strong><\/p>","options":["5cm<sup>3<\/sup>","10cm<sup>3<\/sup>","15cm<sup>3<\/sup>","20cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>HNO<sub>3 <\/sub>+ H<sub>2<\/sub>O -&gt; H<sub>3<\/sub>O<sup>+<\/sup><\/strong>&nbsp; +&nbsp;<strong><sup> <\/sup>NO<sub>3<\/sub><sup>-<\/sup> is the <\/strong><\/p><p><strong>NO<sub>3<\/sub> in the reaction is the?<br><\/strong><\/p>","options":["conjugate acid","acid","conjugate base","base"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>How much NaOH is required to make 250cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.1mol\/dm<sup>3<\/sup> solution&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["10g","1.0g","0.1g","4g"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>A current of 0.5A flows for 1930 seconds and deposits 0.325g of metal M. If the charge is +2, the relative molecular masss is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["65","32.5","24","40.9"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Emission of chlorofluorocarbon (CFC) into the atmosphere causes<\/strong><\/p>","options":["global warming","acid rain","depletion of ozone layer","greenhouse effect"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following samples will react fastest with dilute HCl?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["10g of powered CaCO<sub>3<\/sub> at 25<sup>o<\/sup>C","10g of lumps CaCO<sub>3<\/sub> at 25<sup>o<\/sup>C","10g of lumps of CaCO<sub>3<\/sub> at 50<sup>o<\/sup>C","10g of powered CaCO<sub>3<\/sub> at 50<sup>o<\/sup>C"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>The colour exhibited by copper in a test is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["green","lilac","blue-green","crimson"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following statements is correct?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["chlorine bleaches by oxidation while sulphur(iv)oxide bleaches by reduction","chlorine bleaches by reduction while sulphur(iv)oxide bleaches by oxidation","both of them bleach by oxidation","both of them bleach by reduction"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>2-methylbut-2-ene is an isomer of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["pent-1-ene","2-methylpent-2-ene","hex-3-ene","2-methylprop-1-ene"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"}]